so let's look at the solution to our
multipore versus single core quiz this
is what we had in the old technology in
the new technology one of these scores
is going to be half the size and half
the power
so we had the option of either replacing
that with a better core that occupies
the whole area gets a small IPC but
consumes slightly more power and then
the question is if we do consume the
whole power budget of the chip which is
a hundred watts how much can we increase
this frequency and with that frequency
what is the overall speed up versus what
we had in the old technology
the other option was just put the two
cores that we can now fit on the chip
each now gets us the same IPC as the
single core did and together they
consume the whole power budget of the
chip at 2 gigahertz so the question is
what's the speed up versus the old
technology with the two core approach
the first thing we need to figure out
here is how much can we raise this
frequency here so that we get to 100
Watts well we are allowed to increase
the power from 75 watts to 100 Watts
that's a factor of 1.33 remember that
the dynamic power is proportional to
voltage squared times the frequency
itself and that we have to increase the
voltage in proportion to frequency so if
we are spending power to increase the
frequency we have to proportionally get
both the voltage and the frequency up
and that means that we will be spending
power in proportion to the cube of the
frequency that means that the frequency
that we can operate on is cubic root of
1 to 33 times the old frequency and this
is equal to 1.1 so our new frequency is
1.1 times the old frequency the old
frequency was 2 gigahertz that means we
can achieve 2.2 gigahertz when we
increase the power by a factor of 1.33
the speed up we achieve versus the old
technology will be the speed up we
achieve because of a shorter clock cycle
time and that speed up is 1.1 times
so we are 1.1 times faster now in terms
of clock frequency times the speed up we
achieve because our IPC is better and if
we divide 3.5 and 2.5 we get a factor of
1.4
times
the speed up we achieve because we have
fewer instructions but because we are
executing exactly the same code that
speed up is one we don't speed up really
so our overall speed up is just this and
it ends up being 1.54 now let us look at
the two core option we have the same IPC
as before but we now have two cores that
are doing that so we are executing twice
as many instructions as before at the
same frequency
and at the same power so the speed up
versus the old system here will simply
be two we are operating at the same
frequency splitting the same work into
two pieces and each of the pieces is now
done at the speed where we were doing
only one of the pieces so overall we are
getting a speed up of two as you can see
two cores are achieving a better speed
up relative to the old system than a
fancier core which means that if we
indeed do have programs that can use the
two cores effectively then this is the
better option
than improving the core and consuming
the chip area that way